software engineering radio episode 10
promoting infrastructures part 2
[Music]
this is the second part of the remoting
infrastructure's episode so in the last
episode we introduced basic ideas of
remote communication using
message-oriented and remote procedure
call middleware we introduced the broker
pattern that serves as the basis for our
PC based middleware and so in this
episode we take a look at the details
along the lines of the patterns
described in the remoting patterns book
so I think yeah you start by explaining
the client proxy right yeah the client
proxy is what the client application
sees from the communication middleware
and the client proxy implements the same
interface as the remote object and hides
all the details of serialization and
dispatching a network communication to
the client application in case narrow
occurs the client proxy is the one who
communicates it back to the application
logic the client proxy is a
specialization of the proxy pattern and
reduced by the gulf patterns bug okay so
so the client calls a method on the
proxy thinks it calls the remote method
actually does call the remote method the
proxy then magically will explain how
that works later magically transports
the invocation to the server and what
happens there on the server there is
something we call the invoker and that's
a component that accepts the the request
object something that describes what the
client wants from the server it receives
this object and then dispatches the
invocation to the remote object and so
if the remote object is just a normal
language object you know assume you have
the client that calls a say hello method
and the server also has a say hello
method in its server object then the
invoker is responsible for interpreting
this data structure that transports the
request over the network and then
actually call the say hello method on
the server object on the client side if
we go
the stack one step down below declined
proxy is something that we call the
requester and follows our requester
pattern that requester encapsulate all
the reusable parts that are not in the
client proxy which is specific to a
certain remote object so the requester
needs an absolute object reference to
then tell the lower network layers to
establish a connection to the server
site so try to illustrate that a bit
further the problem here is that the
client proxy and also the server object
have a specific signature a specific
interface which you want to call
natively
however the communication middleware
below it doesn't know about these
specific interfaces otherwise you would
have to rebuild the complete middleware
just if you just do to be able to talk
to a different signature to a different
interface on the server side so the the
requesters job is to translate the
specific signature the specific method
calls that you make on a client proxy
into a generic object that can be
translated over the network and on the
other side the reverse thing happens the
invoker takes this generic data
structure and kind of down casts I know
it's the wrong term but makes the
specific the interface specific call on
the server-side object and to be able to
do that we need something that's called
marshal ER the top of the marshal ER is
to to take the request object basically
an object that says call this method
with those parameters on that object on
the server so and this object has to be
serialized into something that's
transportable over the network this can
be some kind of IAP encoding for
Carbaugh it can be just Java
serialization for RMI it can be some XML
angled bracket thing for web services
and so we have the marshal or on the
client side and on the server side
because on the client side the
marshmallow transforms the request
object into bits and bytes and on the
server side the marshal er
transforms the bits and bytes back into
best object and on the writ for the
return value the same happens the other
way around the marshal on the
server-side takes the return value
description object turns it into bits
and bytes which requests on the client
then re-establishes into an object okay
and at the lowest layer of the layered
architecture we have the client request
Handler and a server request handler
they deal with how the data is put on
the wire how it is read from the wire
and dispatched for example to the
invoker on the server side or the result
to the requester on the client side here
patterns like reactor or leader follower
are used for demultiplexing and
dispatching of events these are the
components that make sure that the
system is scalable and these kinds of
things okay the final part of this kind
of basic set of patterns is the
interface description obviously if you
want to be able to seamlessly talk to a
remote object you have to describe its
interface in some way that doesn't only
allow you as the application programmer
to call the remote object but the
interface also has to be described in a
way that the middleware can actually
understand it and build or set up all
the Rope communications infrastructure
so the the interface description
describes the interfaces the operations
sometimes attributes and the signatures
of the operations and also usually the
exceptions the operations can throw and
what usually happens then is that some
kind of code generator reads the
interface description and generates the
client proxy so application programmers
just have to call off methods on it and
the implementations generated the same
is true for the invoker also sometimes
called skeleton car bot world for
example and this invoker is also often
generated from the interface description
there are other ways of getting this
client proxy and invoker implemented for
example in languages that are more
dynamic you can for example build client
proxies dynamically at runtime for
example in Java there is this dynamic
proxy API where you can just call some
Java API methods and pass in Java
interface and it implements on the fly a
proxy implementation which you can then
use as the client proxy same thing on
the server if there is a way to invoke
methods using reflection for example in
Java then you can implement the invoke
route generically a nice example of what
can be done dynamically is the Spring
Framework there you can basically
implement your application logic in what
they call pojos plain old java objects
and then you can declare using a
configuration file that some objects
have to be accessible remotely or that
some object has to act as a proxy for a
road object and then what spring does
during system startup is it dynamically
generates all the infrastructure that's
necessary and that's really quite cool
what what happened in the last couple of
years is that the remote are the
reflection mechanisms of mainstream
languages have become so fast that using
reflection is not a big performance
problem anymore this is different of
course in embedded systems where you
need to be deterministic with regards to
how many processor cycles or
instructions you use for something but
in you know this general-purpose
enterprise web blah-blah-blah
development
it's absolutely feasible to use dynamic
proxies dynamic invoker's and all that
stuff one last point there another trend
that started in the last two years or so
is that there is this middle path
between statically generating source
code and doing everything dynamically
and that is that you at runtime on the
fly generate bytecode Java bytecode for
example to represent the proxies using
libraries like CG lip or something like
that
so that doesn't require a specific
source code generation step but on the
other hand it also doesn't use dynamic
implementations it on the flight
generates the byte code that then is
used as if it would have been statically
generated so so Michael what are the
consequences of into introducing a
communication will where now that we
have established how it basically works
the consequences are important to
consider because you cannot just develop
an application and distribute objects as
you like you need to be careful when
selecting the places the spots for
remote communication for example
building a distributed system because of
the third reason we mentioned before
because of the non-functional
requirement because they need to achieve
scalability because you need to be
reliable in your system setup you should
be very careful to select the interfaces
on which you introduce remote
communication remote communication is by
an order of magnitude slower and it has
negative that consequences not only on
the performance and a latency delay but
also on error handling remote
communication introduces a whole set a
whole Clause of potential errors that
need to be dealt with in the application
logic because you have now many new
situations where errors could occur
imagine your remote object is not
available anymore either because the
server crashed or because the network is
unavailable you need to deal with those
situations that you didn't have before
when you have a an application only
running on one host either the complete
application failed or it just worked
with the introduction of remoting
middleware the failure could also lie in
the middleware itself and in every case
you need to define how your application
has to react on any failures in between
it's interesting to see that currently
or more recently
trend has started to be important that
basically makes component boundaries and
remoting boundaries more explicit than
before if you look at carbon the idea
was to have remote objects basically
look the same as if they were local you
couldn't distinguish a local call from a
remote call except by that it might be
slower and and raise a couple of more
exceptions if you look at more recent
middleware implementations like for
example windows communication foundation
called indigo a while ago or like the
service-oriented approach to software
development then you know in the
application logic that you call a remote
component you have this remoting of this
component boundary made much more
explicit and that's interesting to see
because a while back people try to make
things simpler by hiding remote in
complexity and now people try to make
things simpler by making this remoting
aspect explicit yeah probably in a
couple of years the opposite trend is
going to show up again another important
topic is the extension of middleware the
extension of the for example third-party
remoting middleware when you need to
integrate additional functionality or
when you need to exchange certain
functionality all three examples that we
discussed here some Kaba web services
and other promoting implementations they
allow the extension of the middle where
the primary mechanisms to achieve that
our invocation interceptors and protocol
plugins invocation and receptors allow
you to intercept data to intercept
requests and responses in the data flow
of the call stack this can be anywhere
in the call stack very low at a
serialized byte stream level or actually
just before dispatching it depends on
what you kind of application
functionality you want to integrate
for example in the case of security when
you need to introduce encryption it's a
good idea to use an interceptor that's
pretty low in the call stack basically
one that operates at a serialized byte
stream level and an example for the
higher-level ones could be transactions
right so you have some transaction ID on
the client and you have to make sure
this ID is transported so you insert the
transaction ID into the request using an
indication interceptor it's transported
over to the server where another
invocation adapter takes this ID and
make sure the request is executed in the
context of a certain transaction usually
you have the a pair of interceptors you
have one that does something on the
client and then you have the one that
does something that's compatible with
the client interceptor on the server
side another way of extending the
middleware is protocol plug-ins so for
example if you want to run carbene
middleware over tcp/ip in the one
instance and in other cases you want to
run Carbaugh over some not so well-known
embedded middleware embedded network
protocols like for example the campus or
something like that then you should be
able to exchange the protocol
implementation inside the middleware so
you'll still be able to use the same
middleware but it uses a different cut
transportation protocol in dotnet
remoting for example you can either
select an XML based transport protocol
or binary one that serializes the data
into yeah bits and bytes and not into
readable human readable XML promoting
middleware is very often used in
combination with component and
application servers and they're the
separation of concerns is typically that
the container is responsible for all the
lifecycle issues of the objects of the
components the services deployed on an
application server and the communication
middleware is responsible for
transmission of the
requests and responses in early days for
example in karma the there was a very
lightweight container the portable
object adapter which took over the
lifecycle management tasks it was
responsible for instantiate and evicting
Kaaba objects if it wasn't done manually
so related patterns here are the
lifecycle manager and all the resource
management patterns such as leasing a
Viktor eager and lazy acquisition to
manage to instantiate and eviction of
remote objects the detailed explanation
of all the resource management patterns
follows in a later episode on resource
management patterns introduced by poser
3 ok so the final thing that needs to be
discussed in the context of remote
communications middleware rpg-style
is asynchronous communication so that
means even if you have basically an RPC
style middleware you can still execute
asynchronous remote procedure calls so
it's not that we now go over to a
messaging middleware we still use RPC
but now we have asynchronous
api's so what does that mean for example
there is something we termed
fire-and-forget you can basically invoke
methods one way so you call an operation
the client infrastructure in this case
the requester and the client request
handler sends away the invocation it
puts it basically on to the wire and
then it doesn't care anymore if the
client gets lucky the request is
transported over the network to the
server where the invocation reaches the
target object and some operation is
executed but it might also just fail it
might not be transported by the IP
infrastructure it might get stuck in the
server the server might have crashed and
you don't even know this so fire and
forget as its name implies it's just you
you call a method and
you hope that it's being executed and of
course this is performance wise quite
good because the client as soon as it
has put the request on to the wire
doesn't care anymore Michael do you want
to explain sink with so ever
yeah sink we're server is also one way
semantics but it is more reliable as
fire-and-forget and the the reason why
it is more reliable is because the
server implementation of the remote
communication framework notifies the
client-side implementation as soon as
the requests arrived on the server side
this is before the request is actually
dispatched to the remote object so the
client doesn't have to wait till the
request is executed but it can be sure
that a request reached to server side
properly and that no network error or
error in the server application or
unavailability of the server application
influenced its remote invocation so that
the the previous two patterns
fire-and-forget in sync with server were
basically only useful for void methods
that didn't throw any exceptions because
there was no way of reporting back the
return value of the operation or
potential application exception so if
you want to do useful or more
sophisticated asynchronous communication
then you have to have a way of how this
is reported back and there are two ways
of doing that one is what we call the
result callback so the idea is that if
the client calls the remote operation it
passes in an object on which the
middleware calls yet another operation
once the result has arrived from the
server so the client invokes the
operation passes in a callback object
the middleware receives the call and
directly returns so the client can go on
doing something else and then the
middleware forwards the message of the
invocation to the server on the server
the object receives the message receives
the method invocation does something
turns some return value that is
transported back over the middle where
infrastructure to the client and now the
client middleware receives this return
value asynchronously and then calls the
callback operation on the object which
declined had provided to the middleware
when it issued the request and that way
the client can have done something else
in the meantime and it's now notified
that the result has arrived
of course this requires an event based
programming style because result
callbacks from any kind of remote
invocation that has been done before can
appear in the client program at any time
it's also not guaranteed that the order
of the callbacks is the same as the
order in which you did the invocations
originally another one is the pull
object the pool object is similar to the
result callback in the sense that it's
also asynchronously notified of the
arrival of the response and the
difference is that the palo check does
not execute any application logic
instantly as the the result callback
does but the palo object needs to be
pulled by the client application whether
the result is already available and
therefore you would use a palo object
when you need to keep your regular
control flow and when you don't want to
switch to a event-driven programming
model okay so i think we have two or
three more patterns in the book but we
don't go into details here so so this
concludes our recollection of the of the
patterns that make up remoting
infrastructures and as we said before
Carbaugh dotnet remoting web services
and basically all other remote procedure
call infrastructures are built along
those patterns so if you want to build
your own one you can now take this
knowledge and and go along and build
your own middleware and maybe just
understand existing middleware
infrastructures better to give you two
proof points that those patterns aren't
something we came up with but our rather
mind from
real systems will not take a look at how
those patterns are implemented in car
bomb and dotnet remoting Michael we'll
start with the explanation of car bomb
in the following I will explain a
typical call by implementation based on
the just introduced patterns to get
started I will explain some kabbaah
terminology first that is on the client
side we typically have a client proxy on
top of the off core the client proxies
to be leet generated from the interface
description on the server side we have
the remote object which is a DEP that by
a so-called skeleton that is also
generated by the via interface
description and below that we have the
portable object adapter acting is kind
of a dispatcher and lifecycle manager
below that we have two server-side all
core the client specific all core parts
implemented patterns requester and
client request Handler while the server
specific op core part implements the
server request Handler both sides have
also a Marshall ER that is responsible
for the serialization and
deserialization of the data the Marshall
or gets used by the client proxy and
server-side skeleton the server-side
skeleton together with a portable object
adapter act basically as invoker as we
just described interception of the call
flow is typically done on the client
side in the stop and on the server side
in the power or discolored on depending
on whether reception is done before or
after serialization by the marsh alert
and receptor can provide a serialize
data stream or individual parameters on
interception as mentioned before the
power is responsible for the lifecycle
management of the remote object
implementations so it can be configured
using a large variety of settings and
specialized handlers to deal with acne
evasion and deactivation of the remote
objects regarding asynchronous
invocations following the pelagic
or the result callback patterns it is
important to know that the server-side
all core is totally oblivious it can be
totally oblivious up that asynchrony
both patterns pole object and result
callback can be implemented using client
specific or core parts only and this is
nice because it avoids complicating the
already complex server-side part of all
implementations that are typically
highly optimized regarding concurrency
and resource utilization and Kaba both
asynchrony models are supported through
the so-called asynchronous method
invocations those are defined in the so
called messaging specification in dotnet
remoting the patterns are also
implemented along the same lines from
10,000 feet as usual a client talks to a
remote app object and this remote object
is hosted by what we call a server
application technically the client proxy
is then represented by a combination of
what the net calls the transparent proxy
and the real proxy the real proxy also
plays the role of the requester and
makes sure that the calls are wrapped in
an object that can be transported over
the network whereas the transparent
proxy resembles the interface of the
remote object on the client side the
reason why those two are separated is
because the transparent proxy is
actually dynamically generated at
runtime from the interface of the remote
object whereas the real proxy is
something that's generic and can be
reused over applications the rest of the
infrastructure on the client side is
built as a chain of so-called sinks a
sink is basically something that accepts
data and does something with it and
spits out the data on the other side so
there is typically a number of sinks
chained together and those built the
infrastructure on the client side the
nice thing is that
can add additional syncs which then
basically play the role of the
invocation interceptors there are two
predefined sinks one is called the
formatter sink and the responsibility of
this one is to transform the logical
object that's transfer that captures
requests into a byte stream or an XML
stream actually there is implementations
for binary transports and XML based
transports so this plays the role of the
marshal or one level below there is the
channel sync and the channel sync
basically plays the role of the protocol
plugin so it's responsible for providing
the transport mechanism itself and then
of course below that there is the dotnet
read dotnet runtime which plays
basically the role of the client request
handler and handles the the low-level
communication issues on the server side
things have basically the same structure
so again there is the dotnet runtime and
going there called other stack upwards
there is again a channel sync which does
all the networking stuff then there is
another format or sync which plays the
role of the Marshall or unmarshal in a
request and then you can as we said
before add a number of other sinks that
play the rule of invocation interceptors
by the way you can add your own sinks at
various locations in this chain you can
add it before the formatter sync or
after the formatter thing which allows
you to intercept the request as an
object if you do it before the formatter
sync or you can also intercept the raw
serialized data binary or XML if you
build your Interceptor into the chain
after the formatter sync there is one
special sync which is called the
dispatcher sync which is basically the
invoker and the lifecycle manager and it
delegates the remote invocation to the
target remote object so a client's
method invocation and a remote object is
basically technically made on the
transparent proxy which builds a request
object and forwards it to the real proxy
it inserts it into the chain of sinks so
the first thing sync but will get the
object is the formatter sync and it will
build
a serialized data structure it then
forwards it to the channel things Inc
which handles the networking issues on
the server side the data stream is
accepted by a channel sync another
channel sync which forwards it to the
formatter sync which D marshals the data
into the request object and forwards it
to the dispatcher sync the dispatcher
playing the role of the invoker uses
reflection to invoke the specific
operation on the remote object a couple
of sentences on lifecycle management
there are two fundamentally different
kinds of life cycles and dotnet one is
what we call the server activated
instances that means the server
application is responsible for creating
and destroying remote objects there are
several ways one is the so-called per
request instance that means that for
each request of the client there is a
new instance created this requires
stateless objects obviously then there
is the static instance which means that
the instance is created explicitly by
the server application and also
destroyed explicitly typically at the
beginning and at the end of the
application server applications lifetime
then there is the lazy acquisition which
is basically the same as static instance
but it's lazily created as soon as the
first request from a client arrives the
other strategy of lifecycle management
is client dependent instances in that
case the client is responsible for
creating the remote object explicitly
it's also responsible for keeping it
alive by extending its lease time we'll
talk about leasing in later episodes
about resource management the interface
description internet remoting is
achieved by using dotnet interfaces a
construct that is native to the donut
platform there is no special interface
definition language asynchronous
communication is also available in net
although it's not specific to that net
remoting it's generally available in
the.net platform using what they call
delegates which is kind of strongly
typed function pointer and as in
car-bomb and in most other middlewares
the asynchronous communications aspects
are handled exclusively on the client so
the server implementation is not
affected by
asynchronous calls so
what the net supports is pole objects
you you call an operation on a specific
delegate and the result is what they
call an instance of the I a sink result
type on which you can Paul for the
result
another possibility is using result
callbacks you have to pass in an object
on which dotnet can do the callback and
finally you can also use one-way
operations by using an annotation dotnet
attribute called one-way on operations
in the interface so before we finish off
this episode we should also take a look
at Microsoft's even newer technology for
remote communication which is called
indigo or Windows communications
foundation it's basically a component
oriented distribution middleware the
core concepts are parts which are
basically network endpoints message
handlers which is a piece of application
logic basically and channels which
connect ports to message handlers we can
map our patterns to this new technology
also channels basically fulfill the role
of the requester and also the invoker
and they can also be configured with
additional behavior such as transactions
or security so they also play the role
of the invocation interceptor ports play
the role of the client and the server
request handlers whereas the remote
object is something is implemented as
part of the message handler that sits at
the far end of the channel so as you can
see even Microsoft's newest technology
can be described with our patterns and
it it helps to understand the patterns
to understand middleware it's probably
not going to change over the next couple
of implementations of middleware the
patterns will probably still be the same
so this concludes this episode something
that we didn't talk about in this
episode is the efficient and scalable
implementation of network communications
and multi-threading and all these kinds
of things we'll planning on creating a
set of episodes on concurrency and all
those really topics and we'll cover
these things there so thanks for
listening and
see you next time
[Music]
this was another episode of software
engineering radio the software
engineering radio team wants to thank
Henning poly for providing the music as
well as lips and comm for hosting in
bandwidth for more information on the
podcast past episodes and feedback go to
s e - radio dotnet
[Music]